Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today’s דף daf is בבא בתרא Bava
Batra קי״ב, kuf yud bet, 112, we pick up two lines from
the top מה ואומר Mah v’omer and we’re in the middle of
a discussion from yesterday about how do we know that a husband
inherits from his wife? If his wife dies, it first goes to
the husband and only if there is no husband does it go
to her children. And the גמרא Gemara tries to learn it out
from different פסוקים psukim but there’s a real problem about how clear
the פסוקים psukim are. One פסוק pasuk is
about ונתתם את נחלתו לשארו הקרוב אליו ממשפחתו וירש אתה, v’natan et
hanachala l’sheiro hakarov eilav mimishpachto v’yarash otah, to his flesh that is
closest to him from his family and should inherit, and that does
not, that sounds like it’s a blood tie and that it is
not, and it’s the man passing it on to his flesh. So
to the degree that we say שארו זו אשתו sheiro zu ishto
because of בשר אחד, basar echad, the word שאר she’er also means
בשר, basar, then it would sound like the wife inherits the husband,
not the opposite way around. So the גמרא Gemara tried to do
things with that פסוק pasuk to have it say that the husband
inherits the wife.
And then we had a whole string of פסוקים psukim here from
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael or וירש אתה v’yarash otah to take it
those two words just by themselves, he should inherit her, take those
out of context. And then we had, that was רבי עקיבא, Rebbi
Akiva, and then we had a whole string of פסוקים psukim from
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael where it speaks about if a woman inherits,
the תורה Torah is concerned that it will pass out of the
שבט. shevet. So, and he said that all of those פסוקים psukim
are to say that it would pass out of the שבט, shevet,
it would go because of a concern that it would go to
her husband, although simply the concern is that it would go to
her son, and the son would be of a different שבט shevet
if her husband was out of a different שבט. shevet. This was
sort of the whole issue with בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzlofchad and why
they were told they had to marry from within the שבט. shevet.
But the רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael says that those are all showing
that if she were to die, it would go to her husband
and then quoted two פסוקים psukim also from later in נ״ך Nach
where it seems like a child could have something that the father,
he did not get from the father, and it says that this
must be because he inherited from his wife. Of course, all of
these can be challenged as the גמרא Gemara will challenge them right
now. And I should mention that it’s because of the weakness or,
you know, of all of these פסוקים psukim and the non-פשט pshat
of the פסוקים psukim that רמב״ם Rambam actually says that the husband
inheriting from his wife is דברי סופרים, D’vrai Sofrim, is rabbinic and
it is not in the תורה. Torah. And that parallels also the
idea that the husband, if he’s a כהן, kohen, becomes טמא tamei
to his wife. You know, the פסוק pasuk sort of says לא
יטמא בעל בעמיו להחלו, lo yitama ba’al b’amav l’heichalo, a husband, or
one way to read that, cannot become טמא tamei to desecrate his
קדושה kedusha for a כהן, kohen, and nevertheless חז״ל Chazal read that
לשארו, l’sheiro, that שארו זו אשתו, sheiro zu ishto, that a husband
is מיטמא mitama if he’s a כהן kohen to his wife, and
רמב״ם Rambam says that that’s also rabbinic, but they made it like
a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. Nobody else has the right to bury
her, only he does, so that’s out of the מת מצוה meis
mitzvah category is how they allowed the כהן kohen to be מיטמא.
mitama. So רמב״ם Rambam learns that these are all rabbinic, but the
גמרא Gemara here sounds like it’s still דאורייתא. d’raita. Okay, and we’re
trying to learn it out now from these פסוקים psukim that show
a concern or a possibility of somebody getting, of it passing not
direct, you know, getting something if from the woman that it would
go to a different שבט. shevet. So let’s take a look. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to go back and look at
all those פסוקים psukim and show that you really can’t learn it
from them. מה ואומר, Mah v’omer, why did you need to quote
multiple פסוקים? psukim? So we started with the פסוק pasuk of רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael where he says וכל בת ירשת נחלה ממטות בני
ישראל. v’chol bat yoreshet nachala mimatot bnei Yisrael. The fact that the
תורה Torah had a command בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzlofchad, or that generation,
as what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, that if they
inherited from their father that they had to marry within the שבט
shevet was so that the land would not go to a different
שבט. shevet. So that shows you, see, says רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael,
that if they were to die it would go to their husband,
it would go to a different שבט. shevet. So the גמרא Gemara
says וכי תימא בסיבת הבן קא קפיד קרא, v’chi teima b’sibat haben
ko kapid kra, no, that’s not about that the husband what inherits,
that could assume the son would inherit, but the son is also
of a different שבט shevet because the son follows the husband. So
how do you know that’s talking that the husband can inherit? אבל
בעל לא ירית, aval ba’al lo yarit, and I would argue that
a husband does not inherit. תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear:
ולא תסב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה אל מטה, v’lo tisov nachala livnei
Yisrael mimateh el mateh, that another פסוק pasuk says that it should
not, you know, go to a different, the, it should not get
diverted from one שבט shevet to another. So why do you need
the extra פסוק? pasuk? You already spoke about it, you know, marrying
within so it doesn’t get diverted. So that must tell you it’s
coming to tell you that there’s another way it can get diverted,
not just going to the son, but it gets diverted also by
going to the husband, which would actually come before the son. וכי
תימא לעבור עליו בלאו ועשה, v’chi teima la’avor alav b’lav v’asei, maybe
that’s not to tell you a הלכה halacha that the father inherits,
excuse me, the husband inherits, it’s to tell you that if you,
this generation בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzlofchad, marry a different שבט, shevet, you
will transgress the positive מצוה. mitzvah. וכל בת ירשת נחלה ממטות אבתיה
תהיה לאשה, Vechol bat yoreshet nachalah mimtot avoteiha tihyeh le'ishah, and you
will transgress the negative ולא תסוב, Velo tisov, because you will have
caused it to be diverted. But that's what those פסוקים pesukim are
telling you, they're not coming to tell you that there's another way
it gets diverted by going to the husband.
תא שמע, Ta shema, so that's why we quoted another פסוק pasuk
even after that, which says pretty much the same as the previous
one, ולא תסוב נחלה ממטה למטה אחר, Velo tisov nachalah mimateh lemateh
acher, it should
not go to a different tribe. So that's clearly, we already know
the positive and the negative, so that extra idea of going to
a different tribe must be to tell you it also gets diverted
by going to the husband. וכי תימא לאו ולאו בשני לאוין ועשה,
Vechi teima lav velav bishnei lavin va'aseh, ah, maybe not, maybe it's
just telling you there'll be another transgression, but still just that it
goes to the son. Now תוספות Tosafot sort of says, it's a
little strange, because normally to get a לאו lav and an עשה
aseh and you need a פסוק, pasuk, those are doing different things,
sure. But if you have another פסוק pasuk rather than just saying
it's adding to the negative prohibitions, it's just duplicating, we normally would
rather say it's coming to teach us something. So, but, so
it's strange that the גמרא Gemara does not say that here, and
you know, maybe that could have been the לימוד, limud, it's an
extra פסוק pasuk and it's coming to teach you it also goes
to the husband. But here we're not saying that, so that wouldn't
be sufficient. So maybe these are all about prohibitions, but not to
tell you it goes to the husband. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
in here, ואלעזר בן אהרן מת, Ve'Elazar ben Aharon met, Elazar the
son of Aharon died, and it said they buried him in the
valley of פנחס Pinchas his son, אלעזר's Elazar son. And the גמרא
Gemara said, how did פנחס Pinchas get it? Why didn't it say
the valley in אלעזר's Elazar valley? How did פנחס Pinchas get property
he didn't inherit from his father? Must be through his wife. He
inherited it, his wife died, and through his wife. So what type
of a proof is that? says the גמרא. Gemara. וכי תימא אלעזר
הוא דנסיב איתתא ומתה וירתה פנחס, Vechi teima Elazar hu denasiv iteta
umeta veyartah Pinchas, maybe not,
maybe he got it through his mother, or maybe he bought it,
which we'll say in a minute. But how do you know that
פנחס Pinchas got it through his wife? Maybe אלעזר Elazar married a
woman, she died, and she passed it on to her
son פנחס. Pinchas. וירתה פנחס, Veyartah Pinchas, תא שמע, Ta shema, come
in here, another פסוק, pasuk, ובשגוב הוליד את יאיר, Uvsegov holid et
Yair, שגוב Segov gave birth to יאיר, Yair, and it said and
יאיר Yair had all of this property in the land of גלעד.
Gilad. How did יאיר Yair get it if he didn't get it
from his father? Why does it say only יאיר Yair had the
property? Didn't שגוב Segov have the property? So it must be he
got it from his wife. וכי תימא התם נמי הכי הוא, Vechi
teima hatam nami hachi hu, maybe same story, how do you know
he got it from his wife? Maybe he got it from his
mother, okay? אם כן תרי קראי למה לי, Im ken terei karai
lamah li, then you wouldn't have needed two פסוקים. pesukim. So since
it's telling me both the story about אלעזר Elazar and the story
about יאיר, Yair, it must be that one is telling, you know,
even though one makes it clear that he inherited from, you know,
he got property elsewhere and maybe I could have said it meant
from his mother, by the fact that you tell me this by
the second story also, that a man had property that his father
didn't have, must be that it's coming to teach me by telling
me this story that he inherited from his wife. Now of course
that's a little bit bizarre, you know, and the רשב"ם Rashbam points
all of this out, who says these פסוקים pesukim are coming to
teach you a הלכה? halakha? Maybe they're just coming to tell you
the story about, you know, what happened.
Why should I assume, and just because it said it twice, like,
you know, one was the story about פנחס Pinchas and אלעזר Elazar
and the other was a story about יאיר Yair and שגוב, Segov,
and nothing is redundant, and they're just coming to tell me the
actual stories of what happened. So like, what is this idea, oh,
it's two פסוקים, pesukim, it's obviously teaching you this הלכה. halakha. It's
very strange, and in essentially the גמרא Gemara asks that question. אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Pappa le'Abaye, so רב פפא
Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, ממאי, Mimay, who tells you that
that's what the story was, that יאיר Yair inherited it from his
wife? דילמא לעולם אימא לך בעל לא ירית, Dilma le'olam eima lach
ba'al lo yarit,
maybe a husband doesn't inherit, וקראי בסיבת הבן
כדשנינן, Vekarai besibat haben kedashninan, and the פסוקים pesukim earlier back about
בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelafchad is because it would go to the son.
And how about these stories here about יאיר Yair וסגוב? v'Segov? יאיר
דזבין מזבין ופנחס נמי דזבין מזבין, Yair d'zavin mazbin uPinchas nami d'zavin
mazbin, and maybe it has nothing to do with them getting it
from their wives or their mothers, maybe they just purchased the property.
Okay, רשב"ם Rashbam also points out you could have said that in
both cases they got it from their mother, meaning it's not coming
to tell you a הלכה, halakha, they just had property their father
didn't have, how do I know where they got it from? They
purchased it, they got it from their mother, you know, why should
I assume they're coming to teach me a הלכה halakha and that
they're duplicate and it's teaching me you get from your wife? None
of this is evident from any of this.
So the גמרא Gemara goes on, אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so אביי Abaye said back to him, no, פנחס
דזבין מזבין לא מצית אמרת, Pinchas d'zavin mazbin lo matzit amrat, basically
you're right, it's a good challenge, this is the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam reads it, it's a good challenge to the רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi
Yishmael position because these פסוקים pesukim might have nothing to do with
it. But I just want to point out that in the story
at least about פנחס, Pinchas, you cannot say that we're talking that
he purchased the property. Why? ואם כן נמצא שדה חוזרת ביובל ונמצא
קובר בקבר שאינו שלו, Ve'im ken nimtza sadeh chozeret biyovel venimtza kover
b'kever she'eno shelo, cause if he purchased it from somebody else and
then he buried his father in that land, it would go back
to the original owner in the יובל, yovel, and then, you know,
his father אלעזר הכהן Elazar HaKohen would be buried in property that
now belongs to some other person that's not staying in the family.
So it can't be that he purchased it. But of course it
might not be that he got it from his wife, could be
he got it from his mother, and then רב פפא Rav Pappa
comes back with a third possibility. Where were we? בקבר שאינו שלו.
B'kever she'eno shelo. אלא אימא דנפלה ליה משדה חרמים. Ela eima dinpala
lei misdei charamin. Okay fine, maybe he didn't get it from, from
he purchased it, but he still didn't necessarily get it from his
wife, he could have gotten it from his mother or he could
have gotten it when somebody puts a field in חרם cherem and
doesn't redeem it, then in the יובל yovel it gets distributed to
the כהנים, Kohanim, you know, and maybe he got it through that
way and then that would not be חוזר ביובל chozer biyovel either.
So a lot of ways he could have gotten the property, there's
no basis to say that these פסוקים psukim are coming to teach
you any particular הלכה, halacha, these stories about יאיר Yair and about
and about אלעזר Elazar and פנחס. Pinchas. So right now we have
sort of left the question about how did we really learn it
from these פסוקים psukim according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. The גמרא
Gemorah on the עמוד ב amud bet is going to get back
to the פסוקים psukim and basically say what the גמרא Gemorah sort
of just sort of said in passing, that we're not if it's
two פסוקים psukim לא תסוב נחלה lo tisev nachala we're not going
to say that it's coming to give you a double לאו. lav.
It's just repeating itself. If we would much rather say they're talking
about different things and not that they're redundant. And therefore one is
talking about going to the son and the other is talking about
going to the husband and that's two ways in which a woman's
property can be redirected. So we are going to say that on
the עמוד ב amud bet to explain רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. But
before or at least parallel ברייתא, braita, parallel to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael makes it clear it's based on לא תסוב lo tisov being
said twice. But before we get to that, we're going to deal
with a somewhat like confused little piece of גמרא Gemorah about a
statement of אביי Abaye that really is not directly talking about the
proof of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael but is talking about the פסוקים
psukim about לא תסוב נחלה. lo tisev nachala. It's not so much
confusing as much as it is seems a little sort of wordy
and and and repetitive, but let's take a look at it. And
I'm going to read this the way the רשב"ם Rashbam understands this.
So let's take a look. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, said אביי, Abaye,
סוף סוף הא קא מתעקרא נחלה משבטא דאימא לשבטא דאבא. sof sof
ha ka mitakra nachala misheivta d'ima l'sheivta d'abba. So the
way the רשב"ם Rashbam understands this has nothing to do with the
proof about a husband inheriting, he's got a different problem. We said
that the פסוק pasuk ממטה אביה mimatei aviah like ולא תסוב נחלה
ממטה v'lo tisev nachala mimatei that we were talking about somebody who
inherited from two מטות. matot. That got בנות צלפחד, bnos tzelofchad, you
know, got from a let's say in their case or in another
case, you know, got from the father from one שבט shevet and
the girl inherited, the woman inherited from her mother from a different
שבט. shevet. Okay, and now she so she now has inheritance from
both ראובן Reuven and
שמעון. Shimon. So and now it's saying that she has to marry
somebody again, this is only from the generation of that generation that
went into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, she has to marry somebody from
ראובן Reuven so the inheritance does not get diverted away from ראובן
Reuven because she inherited from her father from ראובן. Reuven. But says
אביי, Abaye, but if מטות matot is telling you like we said
earlier that she also inherited from a different מטה, mateh, from a
different שבט shevet from her mother from שמעון, Shimon, so אביי Abaye
is saying, so then that property, the mother's property is going to
get diverted to another שבט. shevet. So he says so that's what
אביי Abaye says I just don't understand, סוף סוף הא קא מתעקרא
נחלה משבטא דאימא לשבטא דאבא. sof sof ha ka mitakra nachala misheivta
d'ima l'sheivta d'abba. It's going to be diverted from her mother's שבט
shevet שמעון Shimon to her father's. She's going to marry a man
from ראובן Reuven her father's שבט, shevet, but the mother's property will
be diverted to a different שבט. shevet. So then the גמרא Gemorah
pushes back וממאי ודלמא שאני התם שכבר הוסבה. umimai v'dilma shani hatam
she'kvar husevah. No, maybe the תורה Torah isn't bothered about that. Why?
Because as soon as she inherited, here she was, you know, she's
her father is ראובן Reuven so she's from the ראובן Reuven tribe
and now she inherits from her mother who's from שמעון. Shimon. So
that property, even before she marries another before she marries a man,
that property, the שמעון Shimon property is already in the tribe of
ראובן. Reuven. She inherited it and she's in the tribe of ראובן.
Reuven. So maybe that's why the תורה Torah is not concerned with
her going ahead and marrying somebody from ראובן Reuven because her mother's
שמעון Shimon property is already in the tribe of ראובן, Reuven, it's
in her possession. Now, course by a woman's possession it's going to
be likely be variable because depends who the man is that she'll
marry to or her son or child to decide. she'll marry or
her son or child to decide what שבט shevet it's going to
end up. But right now it's in ראובן. Reuven. So therefore, the
תורה Torah doesn't care that she's going to marry a man from
ראובן. Reuven. The שמעון Shimon property has already been diverted. שכבר
הוסבה. shek'var huspah. אמר ליה, amar lei, so אביי Abaye said back,
שכבר הוסבה לא אמרינן. shek'var huspah lo amrinan. No, I'm not convinced
that that's sufficient. I am still again, this is the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam is reading this, I am still concerned why the
תורה Torah is not
demanding what other solution is there? If she has property from ראובן
Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, what's she supposed to do? One of it
is going to get diverted. But אביי's Abaye saying, it still bothers
me. How can the תורה Torah say marry ראובן? Reuven? This שמעון
Shimon property is now going to get fully, really inherited by a
man or by her son that's from
ראובן. Reuven. And the fact that now it's sort of quasi under,
already in ראובן, Reuven, that to me is not a sufficient explanation
why the תורה's Torah not concerned about it being further diverted. שכבר
הוסבה לא אמרינן. shek'var huspah lo amrinan. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב
אשי, amar lei Rav Yeimar le-Rav Ashi, רב יימר Rav Yeimar said
to רב אשי Rav Ashi here, having heard this discussion, אי אמרת
בשלמא שכבר הוסבה, ei amrat bishlama shek'var huspah, if we gave the
answer that the תורה Torah isn't concerned about the שמעון Shimon property
that she inherited because it's already now, before she marries anybody, in
the ראובן Reuven שבט, shevet, so then היינו דמתוקמא קרא בין בסיבת
הבן בין בסיבת הבעל, hainu demitokma kra bein besibat haben bein besibat
habaal, then I get what the פסוק pasuk is concerned about. Don't,
you have to marry ראובן Reuven because we want to make sure
that that ראובן Reuven property that you got from your father doesn't
get diverted, whether through your husband inheriting or through your son inheriting.
And as far as the שמעון Shimon property, that's already been diverted,
so we're not even concerned about that. So the fact that the
פסוק pasuk says you can only marry somebody from ראובן Reuven makes
sense because our only focus is on the ראובן Reuven property that
she inherited, and it works whether we'll talk about her son inheriting
or her husband inheriting. אלא אי אמרת לא אמרינן שכבר הוסבה, ela
ei amrat lo amrinan shek'var huspah, but if the fact that it's
already been somewhat diverted, the שמעון Shimon property by falling into
her possession is not relevant, that it's still concerned that שמעון Shimon
property should not be further diverted away from שמעון, Shimon, if that's
אביי's Abaye concern and he wants to know what's the answer to
this? So he says, I don't get it. If we were to
be concerned about that, what possible solution could there be? She's either
going to marry somebody from ראובן Reuven or marry somebody from שמעון.
Shimon. You're not going to solve the problem if she has property
from both. אלא, ela,
so he says, אלא אי אמרת לא אמרינן שכבר הוסבה כי מינסבה
לאחד ממשפחת מטה אביה מאי הוי. ela ei amrat lo amrinan shek'var
huspah ki minsava le-achad mimishpachat mateh aviha mai havay. So how is
it solving it? How is marrying somebody from ראובן, Reuven, it's sort
of, again, it seems like we're missing something here, this is the
way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, because it's like we just made
that point, wasn't that just what we were saying? Anyway, but he
says you're not going to solve the problem by marrying somebody from
ראובן. Reuven. הא מתעקרא
נחלה משבטה דאמא לשבטה דאבא. ha mitakra nachala mishevetah de-ima leshevetah de-aba.
So the שמעון Shimon property is now going into ראובן Reuven control
if she marries somebody from ראובן. Reuven. So what possible other solution
could there be? So now we finally see the גמרא's Gemara going
to say what אביי Abaye was sort of getting at, what he
would have wanted to understand that the
תורה's Torah solution that could be the option. דמנסבינן לה לגברא דאבוה
משבטה דאבוה ואימיה משבטה דאימיה. dimenasvinan lah legavra de-avuh mishevetah de-avuh ve-imeih
mishevetah de-imeih.
So maybe she marries somebody just like her. She is descendant, she
got property from her ראובן Reuven father and her שמעון Shimon mother,
and maybe now she has to look to marry somebody who is
descendant both of whose father is from ראובן, Reuven, so he's the
tribe of ראובן, Reuven, and whose mother was from שמעון. Shimon. So
now she comes with both of these properties into the marriage. She
dies, her husband inherits her, or her son, but we'll focus on
her husband. So now the ראובן Reuven property as it was when
she had it, which was in the tribe of ראובן, Reuven, remains
in the tribe of
ראובן. Reuven. And that's now the husband is tribe of ראובן, Reuven,
he's going to pass it down to his son, the son is
the tribe of ראובן. Reuven. The שמעון Shimon property when it was
in her possession was in the tribe of ראובן, Reuven, true, but
it was still somewhat connected to שמעון Shimon because it was being
held by somebody who was descendant from
שמעון. Shimon. Now her husband inherits it. Her husband, it's exactly like
it was before. Being held, just like when she was holding it,
she was in the tribe of ראובן Reuven but her mother was
from שמעון. Shimon. This שמעון Shimon property is staying at the same
level, held by somebody from the tribe of ראובן Reuven and somebody
whose mother is from the tribe of שמעון. Shimon. So that's why
אביי Abaye was saying that actually could have been what the תורה
Torah was getting at. Maybe it says she has to marry ראובן,
Reuven, but maybe also have to account for the mother so that
it's
exactly
like... Going to a person husband father ראובן Reuven mother שמעון. Shimon.
Okay, and by the way, this could also be why this is
relevant to our earlier discussion. This could be part of a proof
that the husband inherits, because the husband can be equal, can be
father ראובן Reuven mother שמעון. Shimon. But if she's marrying this guy
and we're talking only about the son inheriting, the son's father would
be ראובן Reuven and the mother would be ראובן Reuven because she's
from ראובן. Reuven. So, therefore, that might be what אביי Abaye is
getting at. Maybe the תורה Torah is telling us she has to
marry somebody just like her, and that way that would prove that
the husband inherits because then it would transfer, it would exactly, the
property would stay, the שמעון Shimon property would stay not fully under
שמעון, Shimon, but equally at least somewhat would still within the שמעון
Shimon realm. Alright, anyway, so that's what אביי Abaye is suggesting maybe
the פסוקים Psukim mean. Now we get to the עמוד ב. Amud
Bet. You see, it's a very short עמוד ב Amud Bet because
all of this רשב"ם Rashbam was explaining the עמוד א. Amud Aleph.
אי הכי, Ei Hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, הי לאחד ממשפחת מטה אביה ואמה מיבעי ליה.
hai leachad mimishpachat matteh aviha ve-immah mibaei lei.
If that's what the תורה Torah is getting at, then the תורה
Torah should have said you have to marry somebody who is from
your father and mother's tribe. Why did it just say father's tribe?
No, איכתיב הכי, ichtiv hachi, had it written that הוה אמינא אפילו
איפכא. hava amina afilu ipecha. I would have said that it doesn't
matter whether the man she's marrying, her father is from ראובן Reuven
and her mother is from שמעון, Shimon, or her mother's from ראובן
Reuven and her father's from שמעון. Shimon. It wouldn't matter who's from
ראובן Reuven and who's from שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so that's why the
תורה Torah emphasized ממטה אביה. mimatteh aviha. The core focus is that
the fathers be the same tribe, because that ultimately is the tribal
identity. So, since this property that she's holding and she's a descendant
from ראובן's Reuven tribe is now in the ראובן Reuven possession in
the tribe of ראובן, Reuven, even though there's a little שמעון Shimon
going on there with her mother's property, the key is you gotta
marry a man from ראובן, Reuven, okay, so it fundamentally remains within
ראובן. Reuven. And by the way, parenthesis, yes, the mother should also
be שמעון Shimon to deal with the שמעון Shimon property. But it's
necessary that the father be from the same tribe. So therefore it
didn't say מטה אביה ואמה; matteh aviha ve-immah; it said מטה אביה
matteh aviha to underscore that the key focus is the father's tribe
has to be the same. Okay,
now, so that's it. That is the end of אביי's Abaye discussion,
and it's basically either just a hypothetical, like if the פסוקים Psukim
really mean she inherited from both, then maybe she should have to
marry somebody of equal of similar status, of ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon status. But it could also be relevant to our discussion of
husband and son, because the idea that the property retains the same
level of ראובן Reuven שמעון Shimon ownership makes sense if her husband
is inheriting. But her son, that would be, her son would be
a fully ראובן, Reuven, so that's not a way an option. So
if you think the תורה Torah wants to ensure that, then it
shows that the idea that the father inherits, excuse me, the husband
inherits.
Alright, now we're going to go back to the פסוקים Psukim ולא
תסוב נחלה ve-lo tissov nachalah and the repetition of the פסוקים Psukim
to show that as opposed to that they're two לאוין, lavin, that
one is talking about the father and one is talking about the,
excuse me, one is talking about the husband and one is talking
about the son.
תני בסיבת הבן ותני בסיבת הבעל. tani besivah haben vetani besivah habaal.
We learned one ברייתא Baraita that sort of emphasizes the first idea
of the פסוק Pasuk is talking about the son inheriting and the
other that emphasizes the husband inheriting. But actually both ברייתות Baraitas are
going to say that the doubling of the פסוק Pasuk ולא תסוב
נחלה ve-lo tissov nachalah is to tell you both husband and son,
but one sort of starts with son and one starts with husband.
תני בסיבת הבן. tani besivah haben. We taught one that starts with
son. ולא
תסוב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה אל מטה. ve-lo tissov nachalah livnei Yisrael
mimatteh el matteh. It should not go, it should not be diverted
from one from one tribe to another. בסיבת הבן הכתוב מדבר. besivah
haben hakasuv medaber.
That's talking about the son inheriting, okay, which is what we already
sort of know, the husband is the חידוש. chidush. אתה אומר בסיבת
הבן או אינו אלא בסיבת הבעל. ata omer besivah haben o eino
ela besivah habaal. You're telling me it's about being diverted through the
son, maybe it's about being diverted through the husband. כשהוא אומר ולא
תסוב נחלה ממטה אל מטה אחר. keshehu omer ve-lo tissov nachalah mimatteh
el matteh acher. No, the other פסוק, Pasuk, it should not be
diverted to a different
tribe. הרי בסיבת הבעל אמור. harei besivah habaal emur. That's the husband,
okay, because the husband is like a really אחר acher in the
sense that she's marrying in, she's from, you know, ראובן, Reuven, the
husband is from שמעון, Shimon, he's the מטה אחר. matteh acher. Once
she's already married to the guy, her son really isn't from a
מטה אחר, matteh acher, now she's also part of her husband's tribe.
Okay, so but that's so the אחר acher emphasizes the difference, and
that's the marrying out, that is going to the
husband. הרי בסיבת הבעל אמור, harei besivah habaal emur, that diversion
is. of her husband, because הא מני מקיים ולא תסב נחלה לבני
ישראל ממטה למטה בסימת הבן הכתוב מדבר. ha mani mekayem velo tisov
nachala livnei yisrael mimatteh lematteh bisimas haben hakatuv medaber. That's talking about
the son. Okay, so again, the basic point is the doubling up
of the פסוקים, pesukim, one is about the son, it gets diverted,
and the other it gets diverted by going to the father. תניא
אידא, Tanya ida, we'll just read the top of קייג עמוד א,
Kof Yud Gimmel Amud Alef, ולא תסב נחלה ממטה למטה אחר, Velo
tisov nachala mimatteh lematteh acher, this just starts in the reverse direction,
it should not go to another, בסימת הבעל הכתוב מדבר, bisimas habaal
hakasuv medaber, exact same, you know, which פסוק pasuk is about the
husband and which is about the son, this one just starts with
the husband. The different tribe is the husband. אתה אומר בסימת הבעל
או אינו אלא בסימת הבן, Atah omer bisimas habaal o eino ela
bisimas haben, you're saying diverting to the husband but maybe it's really
diverting to the son, כשהוא אומר ולא תסב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה
למטה, keshehu omer velo tisov nachala livnei yisrael mimatteh lematteh, הרי סימת
הבן אמור, harei simas haben emor, no, the פסוק pasuk that doesn't
say אחר, acher, just says from one tribe to the next because
she's already in that tribe, that's talking about the son inheriting, הא
מני מקיים
ולא תסב נחלה ממטה למטה אחר בסימת הבעל הכתוב מדבר, ha mani
mekayem velo tisov nachala mimatteh lematteh acher bisimas habaal hakasuv medaber, but
the פסוק pasuk that says to a different tribe, that's about diverting
to the son. So like we said before by רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi
Yishmael, forgetting about the whole פנחס Pinchas story and the שגוב Seguv
and the יאיר Yair story, it's really about diverting to a different,
it's really about the doubling of the פסוק pasuk of ולא תסב
נחלה, velo tisov nachala, and that is teaching me that it can
be diverted either by going to the son or diverted by going
to the husband. Okay, we'll pick up here tomorrow.